<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title><![CDATA[ Evan&#39;s Blog ]]></title>
    <link>https://evanhstanton.github.io</link>
    <atom:link href="https://evanhstanton.github.io/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description><![CDATA[ The feed of updates to Evan&#39;s Blog ]]></description>
    <item>
  <title><![CDATA[ PostgreSQL Munich Meetup January 2025 ]]></title>
  <link>https://evanhstanton.github.io/munich-meetup-jan2025</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">bic_uQe2YK1rnl0MGUW7ijVZhayOLJDN</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 16:15:37 +0000</pubDate>
  <description><![CDATA[ <p>This was our first, inagural event, and what a success it was! Up front, we would like to extend our appreciation to Amazon Web Services (AWS), who generously hosted and sponsored this event!</p>
<p>It’s also important to extend a special thanks to the individuals who helped make this event possible:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/aleshkova-daria-4480422/">Daria Aleshkova</a> – for her support as co-organizer and for coordinating the venue; it wouldn’t have been possible without her.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ludwigadam/">Ludwig Adam</a> – for his support as co-organizer.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/valeriakaplan/">Valeria Kaplan</a> – for her help in orchestrating the creation of this Meetup Group.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/andreas-scherbaum-87b6663/">Andreas Scherbaum</a> – for his incredible mentorship and help in orchestrating the creation of this Meetup Group.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/floordrees/">Floor Drees</a> – for her incredible mentorship.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/aychingasimov/">Aychin Gasimov</a> – for his role as speaker and technical support.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/farkasp/">Peter Farkas</a> – for his role as speaker.</p></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="contents">Contents</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="#initial-thoughts">Initial thoughts</a></li>
<li><a href="#aychin-gasimov">Aychin Gasimov - What’s new in PostgreSQL 17</a></li>
<li><a href="#peter-farkas">Peter Farkas: FerretDB 2.0, and a step towards a new open standard for Document Databases</a></li>
<li><a href="#getting-involved">Getting involved</a></li>
<li><a href="#closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts</a></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="initial-thoughts">Initial thoughts</h1>
<p><strong>57 RSVP – 30 actual attendees (52.6%, not bad at all!)</strong></p>
<p>Going into this event, I tried to be conscious about finding the balance with a few points: - keeping this a low-key meetup versus a more professional event; - socializing and networking versus hosting and administration.</p>
<p>Looking back, I feel as though a nice harmony was found, though I include my thoughts on improvement within the <a href="#closing-thoughts">closing thoughts</a>.</p>
<p>With regards to the speakers, I personally loved that we experienced two sides of a spectrum; on one side we learned about Postgres internals, while on the other side, more of an ecosystem-wide conversation.</p>
<p>The audience was very engaged, and comprised a mixture of professionals and those much newer to Postgres.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I really feel that success in life can be distilled down to one word: exposure.</p>
</blockquote>
<h1 id="aychin-gasimov">Aychin Gasimov</h1>
<ul>
<li>Talk title: What’s new in PostgreSQL 17</li>
<li>Speaker affiliation: <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/">AWS</a>, Senior Partner Solutions Architect</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/10i6NWnRN5bCWclmUw4kUowYtuy6Z6ccu/edit?pli=1#slide=id.p1">Slides for this presentation</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Aychin gave a nice overview of the new features in the major release 17 of Postgres. I personally found some of the points on event triggers to be surprising. Specifically, as I understand it, that <a href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/17/event-trigger-database-login-example.html">login event triggers</a> didn’t exist prior to this major release! Here are the <a href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/17/release-17.html">official release notes</a> if you’re interested in learning more.</p>
<h1 id="peter-farkas">Peter Farkas</h1>
<ul>
<li>Talk title: FerretDB 2.0, and a step towards a new open standard for Document Databases</li>
<li>Speaker affiliation: <a href="https://www.ferretdb.com/">FerretDB</a>, CEO</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/EvanHStanton/evanhstanton.github.io/blob/main/public/postgres_munich.pdf">Slides for this presentation</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Peter closed the evening with a nice history of SQL and the founding of FerretDB. Their central thesis, as I understand it, is that Postgres (free and open source) can be just as performant in document-oriented operations as proprietary options. From there, he transitioned into the exciting release of FerretDB 2.0, which I found particularly interesting, as I was hands-on with v1.</p>
<h1 id="getting-involved">Getting involved</h1>
<p><a href="https://www.meetup.com/postgresql-meetup-munich/">PostgreSQL Meetup Munich</a> is always looking for speakers and venues.</p>
<p>If you or a friend are interested in speaking on a Postgres-related subject, do consider reaching out! Moreover, if your company is interested in hosting an event, please contact a member of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/postgresql-meetup-munich/members/?op=leaders">Organizational Team</a>.</p>
<p>A Meetup event can be a great opportunity to:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>practice a talk in front of a smaller group, leading up to a conference</p></li>
<li><p>hear community feedback</p></li>
<li><p>share a unique story or perspective</p></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts</h1>
<p>This was a great first event and I’m really looking forward to the next one!</p>
<h4 id="reflections-for-next-time">Reflections for next time:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Include more details on directions to the venue, including parking, for those who arrive by car.</li>
<li>Create more Meetup-group specific social media accounts to consider those who might prefer different platforms.</li>
<li>Increase organization related to event promotion.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="stay-in-touch">Stay in touch</h4>
<p>If you’d like to have a conversation, consider reaching out.</p>
<p>My name is <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/evan-hunter-stanton/">Evan Stanton</a> and I’m always happy to connect.</p> ]]></description>
</item>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[ Brain Health ]]></title>
  <link>https://evanhstanton.github.io/brain-health-pt1</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">bic_OzhJLhNcSbfeDK7HiYmCBA89yxzg</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2024 20:33:04 +0000</pubDate>
  <description><![CDATA[ <p>Like most of you, I try to be resource conscious whenever possible; sometimes I do a good job and other times not so much. But hey, I try to focus not so much on perfection, but rather the pursuit of perfection.</p>
<p>During my previous professional life as a neuroscience researcher, I gained steady exposure to concepts and systems relating to health and wellness. It’s true that there’s a difference between knowing and understanding, and having made such a transition into tech, it’s clear that there are things the other fields are simply not aware of. Take code repository platforms, for example - academics just tend not to have accounts on <a href="https://github.com/">GitHub</a>, <a href="https://about.gitlab.com/">GitLab</a>, or <a href="https://codeberg.org/">Codeberg</a>. Bash scripting, containers, and languages other than python or R? For the most part, forget about it. The same can be said of the tech community and their awareness of some biological concepts that affect their daily lives.</p>
<p>Considering this, I feel I have the opportunity to share some of my learnings and not only explain why the brain is a <strong>very</strong> valuable resource, but express how I feel that it is being mistreated.</p>
<p>So today, I speak for the brain.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Try to focus not so much on perfection, but the pursuit of perfection.</p>
</blockquote>
<h1 id="contents">Contents</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="#why-sleep?">Why sleep?</a></li>
<li><a href="#biological-underpinnings">Biological underpinnings</a></li>
<li><a href="#relationship-to-industry">Relationship to industry</a></li>
<li><a href="#references">References</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="why-sleep">Why sleep?</h2>
<p>Silly question, right? Let me tell you something though: similar to today’s ubiquitous access to food and water, I’m confident that we’re losing touch with how much sleep we really need, and how much of a finite resource it really is. This trifecta is non-negotiable, full stop. Days without water, weeks without food, something something without sleep. Aha - there’s the devil in the details we were looking for. While issues related to dehydration and starvation and pretty well mapped out, comparative issues to sleep deprivation, sleep fragmentation, inconsistent sleep schedules, and so on, are certainly not as “tableside conversation” as the other two.</p>
<p>A lot happens when we sleep, for example memory allocation (Brodt et al., 2023), but for now I’ll focus moreso on brain waste clearance.</p>
<h2 id="biological-underpinnings">Biological underpinnings</h2>
<p>Fun fact: every night when we sleep, the brain washes itself of its naturally-occurring metabolic byproducts (Hablitz et al., 2020; Kroesbergen et al., 2024).</p>
<p>You see, the brain (cerebral) and spinal cord are bathed in a fluid aptly named the cerebrospinal fluid. It travels alongside the arteries, into the brain tissue, and eventually out of that space and processed by the rest of the body. These phenomena are collectively known as the Glymphatic System and has applications in aging, Alzheimer’s disease, traumatic brain injury, and more (Jessen et al., 2015).</p>
<p>This is by no means a stagnant system. Indeed, there are many things that either help or hurt it. Here’s a non-exhaustive list:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Good for Clearance</th>
<th>Bad for Clearance</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Sleep</td>
<td>Sleep fragmentation (Chong et al., 2022)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Exercise (von Holstein-Rathlou, Petersen, &amp; Nedergaard, 2018)</td>
<td>Chronic stress (reviewed by Hablitz and Nedergaard, 2021)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>To keep things managably short, here’s a video I recommend on the subject: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7dmi1bsrsLk">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7dmi1bsrsLk</a>. That said, if you’re looking for something more substantial I’d recommend the work by Rasmussen, Mestre, and Nedergaard (2022).</p>
<h2 id="relationship-to-industry">Relationship to industry</h2>
<p>It’s important to me that I preface this section by emphasizing that I’m not here to tell you that you’re doing things the right or the wrong way. Instead, I wanted to offer you some potentially relevant information that you might not have been aware of. That, and to tie things back to the beginning, explain what I meant when I stated I feel there is a valuable resource is being mistreated.</p>
<p>Our brains are the only ones we’ve got, and in today’s high-tech, fast-paced society, it’s incredibly easy to treat it as a second class citizen; even blame it for not working the way we’d like it to.</p>
<p>Each business or team has their own cultures, rituals, and status quos in place, that might very well be beneficial. However, there sometimes are benefits to taking a step back and asking whether they are indeed helpful, healthy, or necessary in their current state.</p>
<p>Sometimes long hours and trudging along while incredibly stressed is viewed as heroic, when in reality it can be damaging – I mentioned sleep fragmentation and chronic stress as major debilitators of brain waste clearance.</p>
<p>This isn’t meant to be catch-all – some people can get away with lower sleep. Instead, the point is to be aware of these things, and to be aware of industry standards, and where the two overlap for the better or the worse.</p>
<p>So take care of yourself, take care of your team, take care of your employees, and if you haven’t heard of or read the Lorax, by Dr. Seuss, I strongly recommend it – so with that I’ll conclude with a question:</p>
<p>What would the Lorax say?</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>Bohr, T., Hjorth, P. G., Holst, S. C., Hrabětová, S., Kiviniemi, V., Lilius, T., Lundgaard, I., Mardal, K. A., Martens, E. A., Mori, Y., Nägerl, U. V., Nicholson, C., Tannenbaum, A., Thomas, J. H., Tithof, J., Benveniste, H., Iliff, J. J., Kelley, D. H., &amp; Nedergaard, M. (2022). The glymphatic system: Current understanding and modeling. iScience, 25(9), 104987. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2022.104987" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2022.104987</a></p>
<p>Brodt, S., Inostroza, M., Niethard, N., &amp; Born, J. (2023). Sleep-A brain-state serving systems memory consolidation. Neuron, 111(7), 1050–1075. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2023.03.005" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2023.03.005</a></p>
<p>Chong, P. L. H., Garic, D., Shen, M. D., Lundgaard, I., &amp; Schwichtenberg, A. J. (2022). Sleep, cerebrospinal fluid, and the glymphatic system: A systematic review. Sleep medicine reviews, 61, 101572. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.smrv.2021.101572" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.smrv.2021.101572</a></p>
<p>Deng, S., Hu, Y., Chen, S., Xue, Y., Yao, D., Sun, Q., Nedergaard, M., Wang, W., &amp; Ding, F. (2024). Chronic sleep fragmentation impairs brain interstitial clearance in young wildtype mice. Journal of cerebral blood flow and metabolism : official journal of the International Society of Cerebral Blood Flow and Metabolism, 44(9), 1515–1531. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0271678X241230188" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1177/0271678X241230188</a></p>
<p>Hablitz, L. M., Plá, V., Giannetto, M., Vinitsky, H. S., Stæger, F. F., Metcalfe, T., Nguyen, R., Benrais, A., &amp; Nedergaard, M. (2020). Circadian control of brain glymphatic and lymphatic fluid flow. Nature communications, 11(1), 4411. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-020-18115-2" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-020-18115-2</a></p>
<p>Hablitz, L. M., &amp; Nedergaard, M. (2021). The Glymphatic System: A Novel Component of Fundamental Neurobiology. The Journal of neuroscience : the official journal of the Society for Neuroscience, 41(37), 7698–7711. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0619-21.2021" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0619-21.2021</a></p>
<p>Jessen, N. A., Munk, A. S., Lundgaard, I., &amp; Nedergaard, M. (2015). The Glymphatic System: A Beginner’s Guide. Neurochemical research, 40(12), 2583–2599. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11064-015-1581-6" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11064-015-1581-6</a></p>
<p>Kroesbergen, E., Riesselmann, L. V., Gomolka, R. S., Plá, V., Esmail, T., Stenmo, V. H., Kovács, E. R., Nielsen, E. S., Goldman, S. A., Nedergaard, M., Weikop, P., &amp; Mori, Y. (2024). Glymphatic clearance is enhanced during sleep. bioRxiv 2024.08.24.609514; doi: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.08.24.609514" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.08.24.609514</a></p>
<p>Rasmussen, M. K., Mestre, H., &amp; Nedergaard, M. (2022). Fluid transport in the brain. Physiological reviews, 102(2), 1025–1151. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1152/physrev.00031.2020" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1152/physrev.00031.2020</a></p>
<p>The Picower Institute for Learning and Memory. (2023, November 1). Maiken Nedergaard at the MIT Aging Brain Initiative Symposium [Video]. YouTube. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7dmi1bsrsLk&amp;ab_channel=ThePicowerInstituteforLearningandMemory" class="uri">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7dmi1bsrsLk&amp;ab_channel=ThePicowerInstituteforLearningandMemory</a></p>
<p>von Holstein-Rathlou, S., Petersen, N. C., &amp; Nedergaard, M. (2018). Voluntary running enhances glymphatic influx in awake behaving, young mice. Neuroscience letters, 662, 253–258. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neulet.2017.10.035" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neulet.2017.10.035</a></p> ]]></description>
</item>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[ Hello world, ]]></title>
  <link>https://evanhstanton.github.io/hello-world</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">bic_ATas1igzRC6Gs0DnXbv9haf48ojc</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2024 06:44:40 +0000</pubDate>
  <description><![CDATA[ <p>and what a beautiful time it is to be alive! And while I’m certainly not the first to say it, nor will I be the last, allow me to share with excitement that we’re active participants in the age of data, perhaps even golden age. Think about it: the amount of freely available information is apparently infinite and trending towards higher and higher accessbility.</p>
<p>It’s absolutely bonkers to be witnessing paradigm shifts unfold before our very eyes; seeing members of the community bootstrap their way to success, even more excitingly, without the need of a traditional academic degree.</p>
<p>Being something of a scientist myself, I’ve found that one of the most important (and transferable) skillsets is the pursuit of reliable sources of information. In this post, I hope I can share some of the resources I’ve found useful, and perhaps offer a sprinkle of value along the way. This list will evolve continuously.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>At the end of the day, make the decision that’s right for you based on your trusted sources.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="contents">Contents</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="#standards">Standards</a></li>
<li><a href="#documentation">Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="#books">Books</a></li>
<li><a href="#blogs">Blogs</a></li>
<li><a href="#concluding-thoughts">Concluding Thoughts</a></li>
<li><a href="#references">References</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="standards">Standards</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.ietf.org/blog/how-read-rfc/" class="uri">https://www.ietf.org/blog/how-read-rfc/</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/" class="uri">https://www.rfc-editor.org/</a></li>
<li><a href="https://refspecs.linuxfoundation.org/FHS_3.0/fhs/index.html" class="uri">https://refspecs.linuxfoundation.org/FHS_3.0/fhs/index.html</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="documentation">Documentation</h2>
<ul>
<li>rust-lang.org</li>
<li>kubernetes.io</li>
<li>postgresql.org</li>
<li><a href="https://git-scm.com/docs" class="uri">https://git-scm.com/docs</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="books">Books</h2>
<ul>
<li>O’Reilly</li>
<li>No Starch Press</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="blogs">Blogs</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://fossen.dev/">fossen.dev</a></li>
<li><a href="https://paul.af/">paul.af</a></li>
<li><a href="https://tauganet.is/" class="uri">https://tauganet.is/</a></li>
</ul> ]]></description>
</item>

  </channel>
</rss>
